(The drama was based on a book, and all people, organizations,)
(이 드라마는 책을 원작으로 하였으며, 모든 사람, 조직,
(locations, and incidents in this drama are fictitious.)
(본 드라마의 장소와 사건은 허구입니다.)
(It was filmed in accordance with COVID-19 prevention guidelines.)
(코로나19 예방수칙에 따라 촬영되었습니다.)
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
Give them to me. Let me.
나에게 주세요. 하자.
Call 911.
911에 전화하세요.
- What happened? What? - Call 911 now.
- 무슨 일이 있었나요? 무엇? - 지금 911에 전화하세요.
Captain Yoon.
윤 선장.
(Through the Darkness, Part 2)
(어둠을 뚫고 2부)
(Episode 8)
(에피소드 8)
(Police)
(경찰)
Gosh. What's taking them so long?
이런. 왜 그렇게 오래 걸리나요?
It's about the serial killer who murdered wealthy elderly, right?
부유한 노인을 살해한 연쇄살인범 이야기죠?
Come on. Can't you just tell me?
어서 해봐요. 그냥 나한테 말해주면 안 돼?
You're here as a journalist, not my friend.
당신은 내 친구가 아니라 저널리스트로 여기에 왔습니다.
I can't tell you anything.
나는 당신에게 아무것도 말할 수 없습니다.
Gosh. Okay. I got it.
이런. 좋아요. 알겠어요.
Anyway, I'm staying here for the night.
어쨌든, 나는 여기서 하룻밤 묵을 예정이다.
(Seoul Metropolitan Police Agency)
(서울지방경찰청)
- Why are you here? - Hold on.
- 왜 여기 있어요? - 기다리다.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
You cannot enter.
입장하실 수 없습니다.
Come on! Seriously.
어서 해봐요! 진지하게.
Watch me get access to this place!
내가 이 장소에 접근하는 것을 지켜보세요!
(Journalists need access to enter the agency.)
(언론인은 기관에 들어가려면 접근 권한이 필요합니다.)
Any update on Captain Yoon?
윤대위 소식은 없나요?
Luckily, he missed all the vital organs.
운 좋게도 그는 중요한 장기를 모두 놓쳤습니다.
- Darn it. - Hey.
- 젠장. - 여기요.
That scumbag, Gu Young Chun.
그 쓰레기, 구영춘.
- Hey. - Hey.
- 여기요. - 여기요.
How dare he stab a detective?
그가 어떻게 감히 탐정을 찌를 수 있겠는가?
Hey. Control yourself.
여기요. 자신을 통제하십시오.
Don't ruin this.
이것을 망치지 마십시오.
Sir!
선생님!
- Captain Yoon could have... - Hey. What about us?
- 윤 선장은... - 안녕. 우리는 어떻습니까?
What about me?
나는 어떻습니까?
Do you think we're not mad because we have different titles?
직함이 달라서 화난 게 아니라고 생각하시나요?
His rage is understandable!
그의 분노는 이해할 만하다!
My detective got stabbed!
내 형사가 칼에 찔렸어요!
Did you even help her, Song Ha Young?
송하영씨도 도와주셨나요?
How's Captain Yoon?
윤 선장은 잘 지내요?
They treated the wound urgently.
그들은 상처를 긴급하게 치료했습니다.
But the stab wound was pretty deep,
그런데 찔린 상처가 꽤 깊었고,
so she has to stay in the hospital for a few days.
그래서 그녀는 며칠 동안 병원에 입원해야 해요.
I came back after I checked...
확인하고 돌아왔는데..
that they transferred her to a room and she fell asleep.
그들은 그녀를 방으로 옮겼고 그녀는 잠들었습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
Captain Yoon is strong.
윤 선장은 강하다.
She'll be back before you know it.
당신이 알기도 전에 그녀는 돌아올 것이다.
All right. I know that we are all worried about her.
괜찮은. 나는 우리 모두가 그녀에 대해 걱정하고 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So let's calm down.
그러니 진정합시다.
Oh, right. What about our guys in Nojin-dong?
아, 그렇죠. 우리 노진동 친구들은요?
They are working hard to find the bodies, but no news yet.
시신을 찾기 위해 열심히 노력하고 있지만 아직 소식은 없습니다.
What if that jerk lied about burying them in the hill?
그 멍청이가 그들을 언덕에 묻겠다고 거짓말을 하면 어쩌지?
Once we find the bodies, his statement will be credible.
시체를 찾으면 그의 진술이 신빙성이 있을 것입니다.
So we must hurry.
그러니 우리는 서둘러야 합니다.
Okay. Captain Kook is at the scene. So let's give them some time.
좋아요. 국 선장이 현장에 있다. 그러니 그들에게 시간을 좀 주자.
(Scientific Investigations Team)
(과학수사팀)
And one more thing. I'll interrogate him.
그리고 한 가지 더. 내가 그를 심문하겠습니다.
You stay here, Chief Kim.
김 과장님, 여기 계세요.
Are you leaving me out because he got away from me?
그 사람이 나한테서 멀어졌다고 날 외면하는 겁니까?
No. It's not that.
아뇨. 그게 아닙니다.
You cannot interrogate him first.
먼저 그를 심문할 수는 없습니다.
Why not?
왜 안 돼?
I observed him during the interrogation.
나는 심문 중에 그를 관찰했습니다.
And he likes to show off.
그리고 그는 자랑하는 것을 좋아합니다.
He thinks that he can control what's happening to him.
그는 자신에게 일어나는 일을 자신이 통제할 수 있다고 생각합니다.
See? I told you, didn't I?
보다? 내가 말했지, 그렇지?
He kept changing his statements at Mapo Police Station.
그는 마포경찰서에서 진술을 계속 바꾸었다.
It was like he was toying with them!
마치 그 사람들을 가지고 놀고 있는 것 같았어요!
If you go in now,
지금 들어가면,
anyone below you won't be able to interrogate him.
당신 밑에 있는 사람은 그 사람을 심문할 수 없습니다.
If we're not careful,
우리가 조심하지 않으면
he will never talk.
그는 결코 말하지 않을 것입니다.
Did you check if he had any mental illnesses?
정신질환이 있는지 확인해보셨나요?
I did.
그랬어요.
He had a mental illness caused by an epileptic seizure.
그는 간질성 발작으로 인한 정신 질환을 앓고 있었습니다.
According to the records, he was treated from 1992 to 1994.
기록에 따르면 그는 1992년부터 1994년까지 치료를 받았다.
Captain Yoon and I looked into the records of mental illnesses...
윤대위와 정신질환 기록을 살펴보니…
of violent offenders, dating back to five years ago.
5년 전으로 거슬러 올라가는 강력범죄자.
Five years weren't enough, I guess.
5년이면 충분하지 않은 것 같아요.
Your profiling report was correct, though.
하지만 귀하의 프로파일링 보고서는 정확했습니다.
Then let me interrogate him first.
그럼 먼저 그를 심문하겠습니다.
Then you should interrogate him for now.
그렇다면 일단 그를 심문해야 합니다.
Hey.
여기요.
What happened to the woman I stabbed?
내가 찌른 여자는 어떻게 됐나요?
Why?
왜?
I feel bad.
기분이 나빠요.
I don't need to hear your lies.
나는 당신의 거짓말을 들을 필요가 없습니다.
I've got your statement here. So don't try anything funny.
여기에 당신의 진술이 있습니다. 그러니 재미있는 일은 시도하지 마세요.
It was all a lie.
그것은 모두 거짓말이었습니다.
I didn't kill them.
나는 그들을 죽이지 않았습니다.
That scumbag is driving me nuts.
그 쓰레기가 나를 미치게 만들고 있어요.
Then what is this?
그럼 이건 뭐죠?
I wrote it based on what I saw on the news.
뉴스에서 본 내용을 바탕으로 작성했습니다.
It was all over the news, you know. The locations and the method.
뉴스에 다 나오더군요. 위치와 방법.
Is that so?
그렇습니까?
Then why did you lie?
그럼 왜 거짓말을 했나요?
Because you guys forced me to.
너희들이 나에게 강요했기 때문이다.
Right?
오른쪽?
I don't think you have the guts to kill anyone.
내 생각엔 당신에겐 누군가를 죽일 용기가 없다고 생각해요.
You killed 18 people and secretly buried 11 of them?
18명을 죽이고 그 중 11명을 비밀리에 묻었다고요?
It's all a lie.
그것은 모두 거짓말입니다.
Is this fun for you?
이게 재미있나요?
Do you want to know the truth?
진실을 알고 싶나요?
Darn, that arrogant scumbag.
젠장, 그 오만한 쓰레기.
Can I please just go in now?
지금 당장 들어가도 될까요?
Can I not go in?
들어갈 수는 없나요?
I can't let you.
나는 당신을 허락할 수 없습니다.
You're all riled up. If you go in now,
당신은 모두 화를 냈습니다. 지금 들어가면,
things will get even more complicated.
상황은 더욱 복잡해질 것입니다.
Darn it. This is nuts!
젠장. 이건 미친 짓이야!
Who's the boss here?
여기 사장이 누구예요?
If you guys want me to talk, go bring your boss.
내가 얘기하고 싶으면 가서 상사를 데려오세요.
You scum!
쓰레기야!
Do you want a promotion?
승진을 원하시나요?
Don't you get a special promotion for catching a killer like me?
나 같은 킬러를 잡아서 특별 프로모션을 받을 수는 없나요?
You piece of...
당신은 ...
This is why I can't talk to you little fish.
이것이 내가 당신에게 작은 물고기와 말을 할 수 없는 이유입니다.
Go get your boss.
가서 상사를 불러오세요.
I am the suspect in the case where 18 people were killed...
18명 사망 사건의 용의자는 바로 나..
and 11 were secretly buried.
그리고 11명은 비밀리에 묻혔습니다.
That punk is asking for me.
그 새끼가 나한테 요구하는 거야.
Fine, I shall go in if he wants to talk to me.
좋아요, 그가 나와 얘기하고 싶다면 들어가겠습니다.
No, leave it. I'll go in.
아니, 놔둬. 나는 들어갈 것이다.
- What? - Goodness.
- 뭐? - 맙소사.
At this rate,
이 속도로,
he'll ask to speak...
그 사람이 말을 해달라고 할 거에요...
to all the police executives one by one,
모든 경찰 간부들에게 한 명씩,
- don't you think? - Hold on.
- 그렇지 않은 것 같아요? - 기다리다.
One moment.
잠시만요.
- Hi. - Why are you here?
- 안녕. - 왜 여기 있어요?
I didn't want to interrupt.
나는 방해하고 싶지 않았습니다.
- You got what I asked for? - Yes, I have everything.
- 내가 요청한 걸 받았나요? - 네, 다 있어요.
- Hey. - You're still here?
- 여기요. - 아직 여기 있나요?
Where else would I be...
난 또 어디에 있을까...
- These four piles here? - Yes, sir.
- 여기 더미 4개요? - 네, 선생님.
Oh, wait.
아, 잠깐만요.
Take this too just in case,
만일을 대비해 이것도 가져가세요.
Inspector Song.
송 검사님.
You should leave.
당신은 떠나야합니다.
Hey, what is all this?
야 이게 다 뭐야?
Take these inside and just put them on the table.
이것들을 안으로 가져가서 테이블 위에 올려두세요.
Glance at them,
그들을 힐끗 보면,
but don't go through them.
그러나 그것들을 통과하지 마십시오.
To intimidate him, right?
그 사람을 협박하려고 그러는 거겠죠?
Yes, just give him the impression that we already know a lot.
예, 우리가 이미 많은 것을 알고 있다는 인상을 그에게 주십시오.
Okay, got it.
알겠습니다.
- One more thing. - What?
- 한 가지 더. - 무엇?
He gets offended if we use an interrogating tone.
우리가 심문하는 어조를 사용하면 그는 기분이 상합니다.
- It ticks him off. - I see.
- 그게 그 사람을 짜증나게 만드네요. - 알겠어요.
Just coddle him at first.
처음에는 그를 아껴주세요.
Once the real interrogation begins,
본격적인 심문이 시작되면,
he'll lean back in his chair.
그는 의자에 기대어 앉을 것이다.
- Is he a king or what? - All right, I got it.
- 그 사람이 왕인가요? - 알았어, 알았어.
Here, thanks.
여기요. 고마워요.
- No, let me. - Thanks.
- 아니, 그냥 놔둬. - 감사해요.
Just a moment.
잠시만요.
- Take this too. - Okay, got it.
- 이것도 가져가세요. - 알았어, 알았어.
(Robbery Suspect Wanted)
(강도 용의자 수배)
All right.
알았어.
You can talk to me now.
이제 나에게 얘기할 수 있습니다.
Finally, someone on my level.
마지막으로, 내 수준에 맞는 사람.
What's your title?
당신의 직함은 무엇입니까?
Are you the captain?
당신이 선장인가요?
I'm higher than a captain.
나는 선장보다 높다.
I'm a senior superintendent. Four hibiscus flowers.
저는 수석 교육감입니다. 히비스커스 꽃 4개.
I'm the head of Criminal Investigations.
저는 범죄수사팀장입니다.
The head?
머리?
Listen, Gu Young Chun.
들어봐, 구영춘.
Dragging this out will only make things more difficult for you.
이것을 끌어내면 상황이 더 어려워질 뿐입니다.
You know, the cops aren't idiots.
아시다시피 경찰은 바보가 아닙니다.
Let's see.
어디 보자.
My gosh.
맙소사.
You can draw pretty well.
꽤 잘 그릴 수 있어요.
I was pretty good at drawing when I was young.
나는 어렸을 때 그림을 꽤 잘 그렸습니다.
Is that right?
그렇죠?
I see.
알겠어요.
But you know,
하지만 아시다시피,
you drew even the details that we never disclosed to the media.
언론에 공개하지 않은 디테일까지 그려주셨네요.
How did you know these details?
이러한 세부 사항을 어떻게 알았습니까?
Where the safe was...
금고는 어디에 있었나...
and whether it was standing upright or knocked over.
똑바로 서 있었는지 아니면 넘어졌는지.
You even drew these things,
이런 것까지 그렸는데,
which means you were there. Am I wrong?
그건 당신이 거기에 있었다는 뜻이에요. 내가 틀렸나요?
Then...
그럼...
Look at this.
이것 좀 보세요.
Anyone would say this is a picture of you taken from behind.
누가 보면 뒤에서 찍은 사진이라고 하겠지.
And your face is on this thing.
그리고 당신의 얼굴이 이것에 있습니다.
Which means,
즉,
you'll get caught in no time even if you run away.
도망쳐도 금세 잡힐 것이다.
Do you understand?
이해했나요?
Give me...
나에게 ...
some time.
얼마간.
(Seoul Metropolitan Police Agency)
(서울지방경찰청)
We got it. The hill behind Nojin-dong.
우리는 그것을 얻었다. 노진동 뒷산.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
- What happened? - I'll tell you later.
- 무슨 일이에요? - 나중에 말씀드릴게요.
Hey!
여기요!
(Body recovery site, Nojin-dong, Seodaemun-gu)
(서대문구 노진동 시신수습현장)
Captain Kook, we just found one body so far?
국 선장님, 지금까지 시신 한 구 발견했어요?
And...
그리고...
there are ten more?
열 개 더 있어요?
Where did you bury them? You scum!
그것들을 어디에 묻었나요? 쓰레기야!
- Sir. - What?
- 선생님. - 무엇?
Here! Found one!
여기! 하나 찾았어요!
- Over here! We found one too. - Here too!
- 여기요! 우리도 하나 찾았어요. - 여기도요!
- We found something here too. - Hey, dig it up.
- 여기서도 뭔가를 발견했어요. - 이봐, 파헤쳐봐.
This, right here. Hurry.
바로 여기요. 서두르다.
- Here's one too! - Over here too.
- 여기도 있어요! - 여기도요.
Here too!
여기도!
- Here too. - We have something here too.
- 여기도요. - 여기도 뭔가 있어요.
Over here! We found something too!
여기요! 우리도 뭔가를 찾았어요!
Darn...
젠장...
Darn it!
젠장!
This just in.
이게 딱 들어왔어.
The police have arrested a man...
경찰이 한 남성을 체포했습니다..
who murdered 18 innocent civilians in the past year...
지난해 무고한 민간인 18명 살해…
in a grotesque manner.
그로테스크하게.
On the 10th,
10일에는
while investigating the case of the missing sex workers,
실종된 성노동자 사건을 조사하던 중,
the police discovered that the suspect is the same man...
경찰은 용의자가 동일 인물임을 확인했는데…
who murdered four rich elderly couples...
부자 노부부 4쌍 살해한 범인…
around Gangnam and Jongno area.
강남과 종로 일대.
According to the statement of the suspect,
피의자의 진술에 따르면,
the police searched through the hill behind Nojin-dong...
경찰, 노진동 뒷산 수색…
and found the dead bodies buried underground.
지하에 묻힌 시체를 발견했습니다.
They are currently searching through the suspect's home...
현재 용의자 자택 등을 수색 중이다.
to obtain further evidence of his crimes.
그의 범죄에 대한 추가 증거를 얻기 위해.
Here's the report of the case...
사건보고는 이렇습니다...
given by the superintendent of the Seoul Police Agency.
서울경찰청장이 제공한 자료입니다.
Hello, Superintendent Baek Jun Sik of Detective Division, Seoul Agency.
안녕하십니까, 서울청 형사과 백준식 경감님.
Let me brief you on the arrest of Gu Young Chun, the serial killer.
연쇄살인범 구영천 검거소식을 전해드리겠습니다.
The police received a report...
경찰이 신고를 받았는데..
on a serial abduction case of sex workers.
성노동자 연쇄 납치 사건.
On the 5th, around 5:30am,
5일 오전 5시 30분경,
we arrested the perpetrator, Gu Young Chun.
가해자 구영춘을 체포했습니다.
However, Gu Young Chun confessed to having killed...
그런데 구영춘이 살인을 자백했는데..
a total of 18 people.
총 18명.
We took the perpetrator, Gu Young Chun,
가해자 구영춘을 잡았습니다.
to the place he claimed to have buried the bodies,
그가 시체를 묻었다고 주장한 장소로,
the hill behind Nojin-dong, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul.
서울 서대문구 노진동 뒷산.
We found unidentified bodies of women in their 20s and 30s,
20~30대 여성의 신원불명의 시신을 발견했는데,
a total of 11 bodies buried in secret.
총 11구의 시신이 비밀리에 매장되었습니다.
Any additional crimes?
추가 범죄는 없나요?
And accomplices. Does he have any accomplices?
그리고 공범자. 그에게 공범이 있나요?
Thus far in our investigation,
지금까지 우리가 조사한 결과,
we confirmed that he did this alone without an accomplice.
공범자 없이 혼자서 이 일을 했다는 사실을 확인했습니다.
We are also pressing him to find out if he committed additional crimes.
또 추가 범죄를 저질렀는지 확인하기 위해 압박을 가하고 있다.
(Police found 11 buried bodies)
(경찰, 매장된 시신 11구 발견)
This is a hill near Nojin-dong, Seoul.
서울 노진동 인근 언덕입니다.
Once they started digging, you can see the body...
땅을 파기 시작하면 시체가 보입니다...
of a woman in her 20s.
20대 여성의 말이다.
A total of 11 bodies were found in this area.
이 지역에서는 모두 11구의 시신이 발견됐다.
All of the bodies were...
시신은 모두...
- severely damaged. - One interview with Gu first.
- 심하게 손상되었습니다. - 먼저 구씨와의 인터뷰 하나.
There were many trees around where the bodies were buried,
시신이 묻힌 곳 주변에는 나무가 많았고,
and it's also situated deep inside of the hill,
그리고 언덕 깊숙한 곳에 위치해 있어요.
somewhere tough to be spotted from the road.
길에서 발견하기 어려운 곳.
The police are making an attempt to identify...
경찰, 신원 파악 중…
- the bodies found underground. - Is your piece worth some clicks?
- 지하에서 발견된 시체. - 귀하의 작품이 클릭할만한 가치가 있습니까?
The colleagues of these dead women came to the crime scene...
죽은 여성들의 동료들이 사건 현장에 왔는데…
and watched with wretched hearts.
그리고 비참한 마음으로 지켜보았습니다.
("The Worst Killer in History Arrested, Helped by Fate")
("역사상 최악의 살인범 검거, 운명의 도움을 받아")
("Serial Killer Arrested, What If the Police Acted Faster?")
(“연쇄살인범 검거, 경찰이 더 빨리 조치를 취했다면?”)
I think I'm done packing.
이제 짐 싸는 건 다 끝난 것 같아요.
You can just blame him...
그 사람을 비난할 수도 있죠...
for the Southwestern Case too.
남서부 경우에도 마찬가지입니다.
It looks like he did everything.
그가 모든 일을 한 것 같습니다.
He says he didn't do that, so we have to continue to check.
자기는 그런 일을 하지 않았다고 해서 계속 확인을 해봐야 한다고 하더군요.
How can you believe what he says?
그가 말하는 것을 어떻게 믿을 수 있습니까?
Start digging up everything with the premise he's the culprit,
그가 범인이라는 전제하에 모든 것을 파헤치기 시작합니다.
so that he won't be able to make another excuse.
그 사람이 또 다른 변명을 할 수 없도록 말이죠.
I can't quite put a finger on how far his crimes stretch.
나는 그의 범죄가 얼마나 멀리까지 뻗어 있는지 손가락질할 수 없습니다.
We're looking through every other cold case we have,
우리는 다른 모든 미해결 사건을 조사하고 있습니다.
not just the Southwestern Case.
남서부 사건만이 아니다.
Put all of these cases together, then do your best...
이 모든 사건을 종합하고 최선을 다하십시오 ...
to get him to confess.
그에게 고백을 받으려고.
Commissioner, you already know we'll get into bigger trouble...
위원님, 우리가 더 큰 문제에 빠지게 될 거라는 걸 이미 알고 계시죠...
if the prosecution doesn't find any evidence after he's transferred.
송치된 뒤 검찰이 아무런 증거도 찾지 못한 경우.
What we need to do is resolve this pressing incident!
우리가 해야 할 일은 이 긴급한 사건을 해결하는 것입니다!
Try to find a way to avoid responsibility...
책임을 회피할 방법을 찾아보세요...
by turning Gu Young Chun into the perpetrator.
구영춘을 가해자로 만들어서.
With every minute, the media are pumping out stories...
매분마다 언론은 기사를 쏟아내고 있습니다.
on Gu Young Chun and all kinds of other cold cases.
구영천 외 각종 미해결 사건.
We have to throw them something...
우리는 그들에게 뭔가를 던져야 합니다...
to turn away these criticisms that are pointed at us.
우리를 향한 이러한 비판을 외면하기 위해서입니다.
Yes, I understand.
네, 이해합니다.
Are you still trying to see if he committed other crimes?
아직도 그가 다른 범죄를 저질렀는지 알아보고 있나요?
Yes.
예.
Captain Yoon is interrogating him.
윤 대위가 그를 심문하고 있다.
We've been going days without getting any sleep.
우리는 잠도 못 자고 며칠을 보냈어요.
Chief Kim and Captain Yoon are taking turns with the cold cases.
김 과장과 윤 대위가 미해결 사건을 번갈아 가며 맡고 있다.
Man, they are about to blow up trying to humor that man,
아, 그 사람을 유머러스하게 하려고 폭발하려고 하는데,
who's not even human.
인간도 아닌 사람.
He claims to have committed every single case we bring him.
그는 우리가 가져온 모든 사건을 저질렀다고 주장합니다.
He says he would've killed 100 people if he wasn't caught.
잡히지 않았다면 100명을 죽였을 것이라고 한다.
That psycho. Does he think he's some kind of a hero?
그 사이코. 그 사람은 자기가 일종의 영웅이라고 생각하는 걸까요?
Then when we cross him, he'd change his argument right away.
그러다가 우리가 그를 거스르면 그는 즉시 주장을 바꾸곤 했습니다.
He's the first man who didn't budge...
흔들리지 않은 남자는 그 사람이 처음이야...
despite my awful temper.
내 성격이 지독함에도 불구하고.
Ha Young does not bite crazy dogs.
하영이는 미친 개를 물지 않아요.
- You little... - What?
- 너 꼬마... - 뭐?
Hey.
여기요.
How can you still have enough energy to bicker?
어떻게 아직도 말다툼을 할 만큼 충분한 에너지를 가질 수 있습니까?
(The weapon is a size of a camping knife.)
(무기는 캠핑칼만한 크기입니다.)
Another camping knife.
또 다른 캠핑칼.
Yes, we've been trying to see if Gu Young Chun is the perp...
네, 범인이 구영춘인지 알아보려고 했는데...
for the cases in Dongjak and Geumcheon Station.
동작역과 금천역의 경우.
But he denied those.
그러나 그는 그것을 부인했습니다.
- I also doubt this is his doing. - What?
- 나도 이게 그의 짓인지 의심스럽습니다. - 무엇?
Why not? Gu Young Chun said he did this.
왜 안 돼? 구영춘이 그랬다고 하더군요.
I remember reading it on a Daily Case Report.
일일 사례 보고서에서 읽은 기억이 납니다.
This case was already reported. Dongdaemun Station missed it.
이 사건은 이미 보고되었습니다. 동대문역이 놓쳤어요.
This is why we need to improve cooperation between jurisdictions.
이것이 우리가 관할권 간 협력을 강화해야 하는 이유입니다.
I finally get what you mean after going through this.
이 일을 겪은 후에 마침내 당신이 의미하는 바를 이해합니다.
The Analysis Team can be very nosy.
분석팀은 매우 참견할 수 있습니다.
You're always trying to get way too much information.
당신은 항상 너무 많은 정보를 얻으려고 노력하고 있습니다.
- Hey. - Those above tell us to blame him.
- 여기요. - 위 사람들은 우리에게 그를 비난하라고 말합니다.
But these men I dread the most suggest that it can't be him.
그러나 내가 가장 두려워하는 이 사람들은 그 사람이 아닐 것이라고 암시합니다.
But the jerk who actually killed all these people is just...
그런데 실제로 이 사람들을 다 죽인 멍청이는...
Darn it. Man.
젠장. 남성.
Man, unbelievable.
정말 말도 안 돼요.
Captain Yoon is getting his confession...
윤대위가 고백을 받는데..
on the Imyeong-dong case right now.
지금 임명동 사건에 대해서요.
You said his MO or whatever changed.
그의 MO나 뭐든 바뀌었다고 하더군요.
(MO: Modus Operandi, the crime method)
(MO: Modus Operandi, 범죄 수법)
So wouldn't that work?
그러면 효과가 없을까요?
No.
아니요.
This is a whole different case.
이것은 완전히 다른 경우입니다.
Were you after cash?
현금을 찾고 계셨나요?
They were dressed nicely.
그들은 멋지게 옷을 입고 있었습니다.
It looked like they had some money.
돈이 좀 있는 것 같았어요.
I showed my police ID and approached her,
경찰 신분증을 보여주며 다가가더니
but she got scared and began to step back.
하지만 그녀는 겁이 나서 뒤로 물러나기 시작했습니다.
I'm the police!
나는 경찰이다!
Why would she run away?
그녀는 왜 도망갔을까요?
Was it because I looked shabby? I suddenly lost it.
내가 초라해 보였기 때문일까? 갑자기 잃어버렸어요.
(Personal information)
(개인정보)
So?
그래서?
You followed her and stabbed her?
당신이 그녀를 따라가서 그녀를 찔렀나요?
Detective, thanks to me, you'll get a promotion.
형사님, 나 덕분에 승진하실 거예요.
It's my way of paying back for stabbing you.
그게 널 찌른 대가를 치르는 나의 방식이야.
Gu Young Chun.
구영춘.
No matter how much you think, he didn't do the Imyeong-dong case.
아무리 생각해도 그는 임명동 사건을 하지 않았다.
No.
아니요.
He's not the type who would switch from a hammer to a camping knife.
그는 망치에서 캠핑용 칼로 바꾸는 유형이 아닙니다.
I wouldn't say his MO changes.
나는 그의 MO가 변경되었다고 말하지 않을 것입니다.
It simply seems like he was after stronger stimulants.
단순히 더 강한 각성제를 찾고 있었던 것 같습니다.
(Detective Division Conference Room)
(탐정과 회의실)
Are you feeling better?
기분이 나아졌나요?
Yes, I'm all right.
네, 저는 괜찮아요.
I'm glad.
기쁘다.
Goodbye.
안녕히 가세요.
By the way...
그런데...
The Imyeong-dong case...
임명동 사건..
probably wasn't Gu Young Chun, right?
아마 구영춘 아니었나요?
Goodbye.
안녕히 가세요.
The police are conducting further investigation...
경찰, 추가 조사 중…
to find other crimes committed by the serial killer, Gu Young Chun.
연쇄살인범 구영춘이 저지른 또 다른 범죄를 찾기 위해.
Gu claimed to have killed another woman in her 20s...
구씨, 20대 여성 또 살해 주장…
at the end of January in Imyeong-dong, Dongdaemun-gu.
1월말 동대문구 임명동.
The police shared their plans to conduct further investigation.
경찰은 추가 조사를 진행할 계획을 밝혔다.
If he's found to be guilty of the Imyeong-dong Case,
임명동 사건의 유죄가 확정된다면,
- the total number of victims... - What?
- 총 피해자 수는... - 뭐요?
he created will reach...
그가 창조한 것은 도달할 것이다...
- a total of 19 people. - I did that.
- 총 19명입니다. - 내가 그랬어.
The Imyeong-dong Murder Case broke out last January...
지난 1월 발생한 이명동 살인사건..
- in Imyeong-dong, Dongdaemun-gu. - That jerk.
- 동대문구 임명동에 위치. - 그 멍청이.
The victim, Kim, was found lying dead on the street...
피해자 김씨, 길거리에서 숨진 채 발견…
- after getting stabbed many times. - I'll kill you.
- 여러 번 찔린 후. - 내가 당신을 죽일거야.
The case remained unresolved to this day.
이 사건은 현재까지 해결되지 않은 상태로 남아 있습니다.
On the other hand, the police will wrap up the investigation...
한편, 경찰은 수사를 마무리할 예정이다.
and hand him over with the investigation record...
그리고 그에게 수사기록을 넘겨주고...
to the prosecution tomorrow.
내일 검찰에.
He's to be transferred tomorrow, but until today,
그는 내일 전근할 예정인데 오늘까지는
the police believed he has committed more crimes,
경찰은 그가 더 많은 범죄를 저질렀다고 믿었다.
so they have been putting in all manpower into interrogating him.
그래서 그들은 그를 심문하는 데 모든 인력을 투입하고 있습니다.
Why did you choose them as your victims?
왜 그들을 피해자로 선택했나요?
Mr. Gu! Is there a last word you want to leave to the world?
구 씨! 마지막으로 세상에 남기고 싶은 말이 있나요?
I hope this becomes...
나는 이것이되기를 바랍니다 ...
the motivation for women to be more careful...
여성이 더 조심하게 되는 동기..
with themselves.
그들 자신과 함께.
I also hope the riches...
저도 부자가 되었으면 좋겠습니다...
will wake up too.
역시 깨어날 것이다.
Anything else?
다른 건 없나요?
- Mr. Gu! - Excuse me.
- 구씨! - 실례합니다.
- Do you regret this? - Anything else you want to say?
- 후회하시나요? - 또 하고 싶은 말은?
- Just one more word! - Why did you change the MO?
- 한마디만 더! - 왜 MO를 바꾸었나요?
- Do you feel bad for the victims? - Mr. Gu!
-피해자들이 안타까워요? - 구씨!
Just say one more word!
한 마디만 더 해주세요!
(The Safest City, Seoul, Respected Seoul Police)
(가장 안전한 도시, 서울, 존경하는 서울경찰청)
You can't transfer him immediately without a chance for us to see him!
우리가 그를 볼 기회 없이는 그를 즉시 이송할 수 없습니다!
He felt too offended to meet anybody.
그는 누군가를 만나기에는 너무 기분이 상했습니다.
What can I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
Man, all of our staff are trying our best to humor him...
아, 우리 직원 모두가 그를 유머러스하게 만들기 위해 최선을 다하고 있습니다 ...
just to get a word out of his mouth.
그의 입에서 한 마디만 꺼내려고.
He drained us through the interrogation and field search.
그는 심문과 현장 수색을 통해 우리를 소진시켰습니다.
Gu Young Chun isn't an ordinary perp.
구영춘은 평범한 범인이 아니다.
No, he's not ordinary. That's why we must see him.
아니요, 그는 평범하지 않습니다. 그렇기 때문에 우리는 그를 만나야 합니다.
I'll be there soon.
곧 갈게요.
He refuses to meet anybody. What can I do?
그는 누구와도 만나기를 거부합니다. 어떻게 해야 하나요?
He murdered over 20 victims if you include...
그는 포함하면 20명 이상의 희생자를 살해했습니다.
other crimes he claimed to have committed.
그가 저질렀다고 주장하는 다른 범죄.
If you rub him the wrong way, he might change his statement again.
당신이 그를 잘못된 방향으로 문지르면 그는 자신의 말을 다시 바꿀 수도 있습니다.
It'll make our lives miserable.
그것은 우리의 삶을 비참하게 만들 것입니다.
I'm going home.
나는 집에 갈거야.
Is it that hard to do? Gil Pyo.
그게 그렇게 어려운 일인가요? 길 표.
A profiler's question is...
프로파일러의 질문은...
a sort of enticement.
일종의 유혹.
To get what we want,
우리가 원하는 것을 얻으려면,
we must fully understand our suspects.
우리는 용의자를 완전히 이해해야 합니다.
And to understand Gu Young Chun, I must become him now...
그리고 구영춘을 이해하려면 지금 내가 그 사람이 되어야 하는데...
and suppress my anger for a moment.
그리고 잠시 동안 내 분노를 억제하십시오.
I am...
나는...
you now.
지금 당신.
(Seoul Detention Center)
(서울구치소)
- It's good. - Okay.
- 좋아요. - 좋아요.
(Keep quiet)
(조용히 하세요)
It's cloudy today.
오늘은 날씨가 흐려요.
The investigation was over.
조사는 끝났습니다.
What else is there left?
또 무엇이 남았나요?
We're not investigators.
우리는 조사관이 아닙니다.
Aren't you detectives?
당신들은 형사 아닌가요?
You were there when I was arrested.
내가 체포됐을 때 당신은 거기 있었어요.
I used to be. But not now.
나는 그랬다. 하지만 지금은 아닙니다.
Then what do you do?
그러면 당신은 무엇을 합니까?
Our job is to find out the causes behind these incidents...
우리의 임무는 이러한 사건의 원인을 찾아내는 것입니다.
and analyze the causes.
그리고 원인을 분석해보세요.
So...
그래서...
are you like criminal behavioral analysts?
당신은 범죄 행동 분석가와 같나요?
Like psychologists?
심리학자처럼요?
Something like that. So you know what we do.
그런 것. 그래서 당신은 우리가 무엇을하는지 알고 있습니다.
Most people don't.
대부분의 사람들은 그렇지 않습니다.
I was curious about my psychology too.
내 심리도 궁금했다.
I wondered about that.
나는 그것이 궁금했다.
All right.
괜찮은.
Then before we discuss that,
그럼 그 문제를 논의하기 전에,
why don't we go over some questions we have about each case?
각 사례에 대해 몇 가지 질문을 살펴보는 것이 어떨까요?
Sure.
확신하는.
The man next to me is the captain.
내 옆에 있는 사람이 선장이다.
He'll ask you those questions.
그는 당신에게 그런 질문을 할 것입니다.
First of all, why did you make your own murder weapon?
우선 살인무기를 왜 직접 만들었나요?
At first, I used a knife and tried it out on a dog.
처음에는 칼을 사용하여 개에게 시험해 보았습니다.
But the dog kept bleeding...
그런데 개는 계속 피를 흘렸습니다...
and ran away instead of dying.
죽지 않고 도망갔습니다.
So I switched to a steel hammer.
그래서 강철 망치로 바꿨습니다.
A long handle was cumbersome when I grabbed it.
손잡이가 길어서 잡을 때 불편했어요.
And it didn't fit my bag either.
그리고 그것은 내 가방에도 맞지 않았습니다.
So I shortened it.
그래서 줄여봤습니다.
Why did you stop killing after an APB was issued?
APB가 발부된 후 살인을 중단한 이유는 무엇입니까?
You say you are a criminal behavioral analyst.
당신은 범죄 행동 분석가라고 하더군요.
Isn't that obvious?
당연하지 않나요?
The entire country saw a photo of my back. I had to be careful.
온 국민이 내 뒷모습 사진을 봤다. 조심해야 했어요.
Right.
오른쪽.
So we could suspect that you were a careful guy.
그래서 우리는 당신이 조심스러운 사람이라고 의심할 수 있었습니다.
And you didn't leave any evidence when you were new to this...
그리고 넌 이 일을 처음 접했을 때 아무런 증거도 남기지 않았어...
because you were careful.
왜냐하면 당신은 조심했기 때문입니다.
You bet.
당신은 내기했다.
Perfect crimes require thorough planning.
완전범죄에는 철저한 계획이 필요합니다.
There are no perfect crimes.
완전범죄는 없습니다.
You failed to catch me.
당신은 나를 잡지 못했습니다.
We got you. So you're here.
우리는 당신을 잡았습니다. 그래서 당신은 여기 있습니다.
No, I'm here because of my confession.
아니, 고백 때문에 여기까지 왔습니다.
Well,
글쎄,
you said in your statement that you started a fire...
당신은 진술서에서 화재를 일으켰다고 말했어요.
in Hwanghwa-dong to remove any possible bloodstains from you.
황화동에서 혈흔을 모두 제거해 드립니다.
I wanted to break the safe.
금고를 부수고 싶었어요.
I even used a golf club and a crowbar.
골프채와 쇠지렛대도 사용했어요.
But I couldn't open it. I only ended up hurting my hand.
그러나 나는 그것을 열 수 없었다. 결국 손만 다쳤어요.
I guess safes in Korea are pretty sturdy.
한국의 금고는 꽤 튼튼한 것 같아요.
The fire was put out quickly.
불은 빨리 진압되었습니다.
I know. I watched it nearby.
알아요. 근처에서 봤어요.
Were you watching it to make sure it was burning?
불이 붙었는지 확인하려고 지켜보고 있었나요?
I was anxious. So I watched the house from afar.
나는 불안했다. 그래서 나는 멀리서 그 집을 지켜보았다.
By the way, starting a fire wasn't easy either.
그런데 불을 피우는 것도 쉽지 않았다.
Gosh. I had no idea it would go out that fast.
이런. 그렇게 빨리 나갈 줄은 몰랐어요.
The fire went out pretty fast.
불은 꽤 빨리 꺼졌습니다.
Weren't you worried that we might have found your blood?
우리가 당신의 피를 찾을까봐 걱정하지 않았나요?
I didn't think much of it.
나는 그것에 대해 많이 생각하지 않았습니다.
Well, why did you steal the jacket when you left?
그런데 왜 떠날 때 재킷을 훔쳤나요?
I ran into an unexpected situation.
예상치 못한 상황에 직면하게 되었습니다.
So I was nervous. And it got a bit cold.
그래서 긴장했어요. 그리고 조금 추워졌습니다.
I had a lot of blood on my clothes.
옷에 피가 많이 묻었어요.
And I happened to see it. So I grabbed it and put it on.
그리고 우연히 보게 됐어요. 그래서 그것을 잡고 입었습니다.
And you threw it out afterward?
그리고 나중에 버렸나요?
I gave it to a homeless man on my way home.
집에 가는 길에 노숙자에게 주었어요.
Did you throw out the hiking boots?
등산화를 버렸나요?
I threw them out because that was on the posters.
포스터에 그런 내용이 있어서 버렸어요.
You were very careful indeed.
정말 조심하셨어요.
What did you do with the clothes that had blood on?
피 묻은 옷은 어떻게 했어요?
Based on your statement, you didn't change your clothes.
진술에 따르면 옷을 갈아입지 않은 것으로 나타났습니다.
People don't care if you have blood on your clothes.
사람들은 옷에 피가 묻어도 상관하지 않습니다.
When I got nervous about it,
그 일로 불안해졌을 때,
I went into a restroom at a building or a subway station to wipe it.
건물 화장실이나 지하철역에 가서 닦았어요.
Everyone is busy with their own lives.
다들 자기 생활하느라 바쁘네요.
People aren't that interested in other people.
사람들은 다른 사람에게 그다지 관심이 없습니다.
They would only be interested in someone like me.
그들은 나 같은 사람에게만 관심을 가질 것입니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
You've never seen a killer like me, right?
나 같은 킬러는 본 적 없지?
Do you think you're special?
당신은 당신이 특별하다고 생각하십니까?
Isn't that why you guys came here to see me?
그래서 너희들이 나를 만나러 여기 온 게 아니냐?
You're asking a lot of questions too.
질문도 많이 하십니다.
We want to know the type of people who commit crimes like you.
우리는 당신과 같은 범죄를 저지르는 사람들의 유형을 알고 싶습니다.
But we're not interested in you, per se.
하지만 우리는 본질적으로 당신에게 관심이 없습니다.
I'll continue with the questions.
질문을 계속하겠습니다.
Let's look at the murder cases with the elderly.
노인 살인 사건을 살펴보자.
Houses without any security systems in that rich neighborhood...
그 부유한 동네에 보안 시스템도 없는 집이라니...
Gu Young Chun is a different type of criminal we've met so far.
구영춘은 지금까지 우리가 만난 범죄자와는 다른 유형의 범죄자다.
Observing his attitude from the interrogation,
심문을 통해 그의 태도를 관찰한 결과,
he was confident that he didn't leave any evidence behind...
그 사람은 아무런 증거도 남기지 않았다고 확신했는데...
and had a sense of superiority about his crimes.
자신의 범죄에 대해 우월감을 느꼈습니다.
I noticed that too when he admitted his crimes.
나는 그가 자신의 범죄를 인정했을 때에도 그 점을 알아차렸습니다.
Our approach needs to be a bit more thorough.
우리의 접근 방식은 좀 더 철저해야 합니다.
Like how?
어떻게요?
For example, we don't have to...
예를 들어, 그럴 필요는 없습니다...
directly let him know that he chose easy locations.
그가 쉬운 위치를 선택했다는 것을 직접적으로 알립니다.
So you don't want to provoke him?
그럼 그를 자극하고 싶지 않나요?
Right.
오른쪽.
Other than the security systems,
보안시스템 외에
was there a factor you considered when choosing locations?
장소를 선택할 때 고려한 요소가 있었나요?
Security systems? I don't know about them.
보안 시스템? 나는 그들에 대해 모른다.
I just chose a house close to a church.
그냥 교회에서 가까운 집을 골랐어요.
A church? Why?
교회요? 왜?
The deity is right next-door, but He won't help.
신은 바로 옆집에 있지만 도움을 주지는 않습니다.
And I wanted to prove that.
그리고 나는 그것을 증명하고 싶었습니다.
I was the one who decided that they would die or live.
그들이 죽을지 살지 결정한 사람은 바로 나였다.
Have you ever thought that the deity didn't help you?
신이 당신을 돕지 않는다고 생각한 적이 있습니까?
A lot of times.
여러 번.
I always thought so.
나는 항상 그렇게 생각했습니다.
I got caught stealing at the age of 20 and had to stand trial.
나는 20살에 도둑질을 하다 붙잡혀 재판을 받아야 했습니다.
My lawyer said I would get off with probation.
내 변호사는 내가 집행유예를 받고 석방될 것이라고 말했습니다.
And...
그리고...
I desperately begged that I would live a good life...
잘살아달라고 간절히 빌었는데..
if He would keep me away from prison.
나를 감옥에 가두지 않으신다면.
But He didn't do that.
그러나 그분은 그렇게 하지 않으셨습니다.
So...
그래서...
is that why you think He abandoned you?
그래서 그가 당신을 버렸다고 생각하시나요?
Who abandoned whom?
누가 누구를 버렸나요?
People who believe in Him are pathetic.
그를 믿는 사람들은 한심합니다.
They pretend to be holy, but they chase money...
거룩한 척 하면서 돈을 쫓는구나...
and look down on other people.
그리고 다른 사람을 내려다보세요.
Have you been to my house?
우리 집에 가본 적 있어요?
Yes.
예.
You know the bathroom threshold?
화장실 문지방을 아시나요?
The threshold is...
문턱은...
the line that separates the living realm and underworld.
살아있는 영역과 지하 세계를 구분하는 선.
The line between life and death which is decided and ruled by me.
삶과 죽음의 경계는 내가 결정하고 지배한다.
Anyone who crossed that threshold didn't make it out alive.
그 문턱을 넘은 사람은 누구도 살아서 나오지 못했습니다.
Why did you cut up the bodies before abandoning them?
왜 시신을 버리기 전에 토막냈나요?
It must not have been easy.
쉽지 않았을 거에요.
Have you killed anyone?
사람을 죽인 적 있나요?
If I had,
내가 그랬다면,
we wouldn't be here.
우리는 여기에 없을 것입니다.
Right.
오른쪽.
You would be in there with me.
당신은 나와 함께 거기에 있을 것입니다.
If you haven't done it,
아직 안 해보셨다면,
how do you know it's hard?
힘든지 어떻게 알아?
Have you met with other murderers?
다른 살인자들을 만나본 적 있나요?
That's our job.
그게 우리 일이에요.
Of course, it wasn't easy.
물론 쉽지는 않았습니다.
To liven up the mood,
분위기를 북돋우기 위해,
I played grand music when I worked on the bodies.
나는 시체를 작업할 때 웅장한 음악을 연주했습니다.
Why? Were you scared?
왜? 겁이 났나요?
Give me a piece of paper and a pen.
나에게 종이 한 장과 펜을 주세요.
I can't. But why?
나는 할 수 없다. 그런데 왜?
Do you think I'm going to kill you with a pen?
내가 펜으로 당신을 죽일 것 같아요?
Are you scared of me when all my limbs are bound?
내 팔다리가 다 묶여 있는데 내가 무서워요?
You seemed curious to know how I cut the bodies.
당신은 내가 시체를 어떻게 자르는지 궁금해하는 것 같았습니다.
I was going to draw it for you.
나는 당신을 위해 그것을 그릴 예정이었습니다.
The X-ray on the wall.
벽에 걸린 엑스레이.
Was it for this?
이것을 위해서였나요?
That's right.
좋아요.
I studied a lot.
나는 많이 공부했다.
I also read a lot of books on forensic pathology.
법병리학에 관한 책도 많이 읽었습니다.
They tell you...
그들은 당신에게 말한다...
exactly when and where to cut to make the job easier.
작업을 더 쉽게 하기 위해 언제, 어디서 절단해야 하는지 정확히 알 수 있습니다.
All that effort for what?
그 모든 노력은 무엇을 위한 것입니까?
You see, people don't die easily.
아시다시피 사람은 쉽게 죽지 않습니다.
They're not small, and to survive...
그들은 작지 않고, 살아남기 위해...
You already said that was why you chose the steel hammer.
그래서 강철 망치를 선택했다고 이미 말씀하셨죠.
Right. I did, didn't I?
오른쪽. 내가 그랬지, 그렇지?
Then did you know this?
그럼 이걸 알았어?
Before you chop up a body,
시체를 자르기 전에,
you should drain the blood out and wait until the body stiffens.
피를 빼내고 몸이 굳을 때까지 기다려야 합니다.
Then it's much easier.
그러면 훨씬 쉽습니다.
Whatever you do, you should do it in the most efficient way.
무슨 일을 하든 가장 효율적인 방법으로 해야 합니다.
"Efficient?"
"효율적인?"
And to be efficient, you need to study.
그리고 효율적으로 공부하려면 공부해야 합니다.
I bet no one here knows more about human anatomy than I do.
여기 나보다 인체 해부학에 대해 더 잘 아는 사람은 없을 것입니다.
I'm sure I know way more than the two of you do.
나는 당신들 둘보다 훨씬 더 많은 것을 알고 있다고 확신합니다.
You sure had to be "efficient"...
당신은 확실히 "효율적"이어야 했습니다...
to take care of 11 bodies.
11구의 시신을 처리해야 합니다.
Then why did you mark the spots where you buried the bodies?
그렇다면 시신을 묻은 곳은 왜 표시한 걸까요?
Why did he leave a mark only he would recognize?
왜 그는 자신만이 알아볼 수 있는 흔적을 남겼습니까?
Was it a type of sentimental act, to remember what he did?
그가 한 일을 기억하는 것은 일종의 감상적인 행동이었습니까?
To bury other bodies there, time after time,
거기에 다른 시신을 묻어주기 위해,
I had to remember the spots so I wouldn't dig them up again.
다시는 파헤쳐지지 않도록 그 지점을 기억해야 했습니다.
And they'd be uncomfortable too, even though they're dead.
그리고 그들은 죽어도 불편할 것입니다.
I chose the spot so they could hear the stream nearby.
근처에서 시냇물 소리를 들을 수 있는 곳을 선택했어요.
I was being considerate so they wouldn't be bored.
지루해하지 않도록 배려하고 있었어요.
Anyway, I did that a few times and got used to it.
아무튼 몇 번 하다보니 익숙해졌어요.
I was wrong to expect that the devil would have feelings.
악마가 감정을 가질 것이라고 예상한 것은 틀렸습니다.
He has no emotions.
그는 감정이 없습니다.
All he cares about is comforting himself...
그 사람이 관심 있는 건 자신을 위로하는 것 뿐인데...
and justifying his actions.
그리고 그의 행동을 정당화합니다.
Is that why you desecrated the bodies?
그래서 시신을 모독한 걸까요?
You see, I'm a very curious person.
아시다시피 저는 호기심이 많은 사람이에요.
After killing someone,
사람을 죽인 후,
what's next?
다음은 무엇입니까?
I chopped up the body.
몸통을 잘랐습니다.
Then what's next?
그러면 다음은 무엇입니까?
Have you heard of Richard Chase?
리차드 체이스(Richard Chase)에 대해 들어보셨나요?
No, never.
아니, 절대로.
He's an American serial killer who drank his victims' blood.
그는 피해자의 피를 마신 미국의 연쇄 살인범입니다.
He suffered from schizophrenia,
그는 정신분열증을 앓았고,
so he desecrated the victims and ate their remains.
그래서 그는 희생자들을 모독하고 그들의 유해를 먹었습니다.
But he just did it in a crazy state...
그런데 그 사람은 미친 상태에서 그런 짓을 했을 뿐이고...
without any knowledge of anatomy.
해부학에 대한 지식도 없이.
But that's not what I did.
그러나 그것은 내가 한 일이 아닙니다.
I'm different.
나는 다르다.
I see that you studied a lot about murder.
살인에 대해 공부를 많이 하신 것 같아요.
I enjoy studying because I'm a curious person.
나는 호기심이 많은 사람이기 때문에 공부하는 것을 좋아합니다.
Let's take a break for lunch. We can resume after lunch.
점심 먹으러 잠시 쉬자. 점심 식사 후에 재개할 수 있습니다.
Can you eat after hearing all this?
이 말을 다 듣고 나면 먹을 수 있나요?
(Snack Shop)
(간식 가게)
I wanted to curse at him so badly. I had to bite my tongue.
나는 그를 몹시 욕하고 싶었다. 혀를 깨물어야 했어요.
I'll get a bottle of water.
물 한 병 가져올게요.
I want another bottle too.
나도 한 병 더 갖고 싶어.
- I bet you have no appetite now. - No, I don't want to eat.
- 이제 식욕이 없을 것 같아요. - 아니, 난 먹고 싶지 않아요.
It's a dollar.
1달러입니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
After the break, you should go in alone.
휴식 후에는 혼자 들어가세요.
I'm just so angry. I'm afraid I'd ruin it.
정말 화가 났어요. 내가 그것을 망칠 까봐 두렵습니다.
I think it's better that you go in alone...
혼자 들어가는 게 나을 것 같은데...
to make sure we don't fall for his tricks.
우리가 그의 속임수에 넘어가지 않도록 하기 위해서요.
We might be overestimating someone who's just a crazy loser.
우리는 그저 미친 패자에 불과한 누군가를 과대평가하고 있을지도 모릅니다.
From now on, I'm going to deal with him my own way.
이제부터 나는 내 방식대로 그 사람을 대할 것이다.
Where did the other one go?
다른 하나는 어디로 갔나요?
I guess you're pretty brave.
당신은 꽤 용감한 것 같아요.
We heard enough about the case, so I came in alone.
그 사건에 대해 충분히 들었기 때문에 저는 혼자 들어왔습니다.
Then what do you want to talk about now?
그렇다면 지금 무슨 이야기를 하고 싶으신가요?
Why did you confess to the Imyeong-dong case?
임명동 사건을 자백한 이유는?
You didn't do it.
당신은 그것을하지 않았습니다.
Well, have you ever wondered how you ended up like this?
글쎄, 당신이 어떻게 이렇게 되었는지 궁금해 본 적 있나요?
Don't people like me all have the same story?
나 같은 사람들은 다 똑같은 이야기를 갖고 있지 않은가?
An abusive father.
학대하는 아버지.
And no one to lean on. I had a miserable childhood.
그리고 기댈 사람도 없습니다. 나는 불행한 어린 시절을 보냈습니다.
So do you blame your father?
그럼 당신은 아버지를 비난합니까?
I bet you have no idea what it's like to live with a dad...
아마 당신은 아빠와 함께 사는 것이 어떤 것인지 전혀 모르실 겁니다...
who threatens you with a hammer every time he gets drunk.
술에 취하면 망치로 위협하는 사람.
I never lived with my father.
나는 아버지와 함께 살아본 적이 없습니다.
He passed away the day I was born.
그는 내가 태어난 날 세상을 떠났습니다.
You're lucky.
당신은 운이 좋다.
Not having one is better than growing up with a father like that.
그런 아버지 밑에서 자라는 것보다는 차라리 없는 것이 낫습니다.
It's only natural to become all twisted.
모두 뒤틀리는 것은 당연하다.
You think that's the reason?
그게 이유라고 생각하시나요?
Didn't you say you're a criminal behavioral analyst?
범죄 행동 분석가라고 하지 않았나요?
Didn't you hear such a childhood...
그런 어린 시절을 듣지 못했습니까?
could cause you to become a serial killer?
당신을 연쇄 살인범으로 만들 수 있나요?
You see, the prison is full of them.
보시다시피 감옥은 그들로 가득 차 있습니다.
People like me who have no one to lean on.
나처럼 기댈 사람 하나 없는 사람들.
People who are all alone in this world.
이 세상에 혼자인 사람들.
Why did you start...
왜 시작했는가...
luring your victims to your home...
피해자를 집으로 유인하는 중...
instead of breaking into their homes?
집에 침입하는 대신?
Like I said, it was because my home...
말했듯이, 우리 집 때문이었어...
was the place where I decided whether or not they could live.
그들이 살 수 있는지 여부를 결정하는 곳이었습니다.
Not because you were afraid...
네가 두려워서가 아니라...
you'd be caught after you saw the security footage?
보안 영상을 본 후에 잡힐 거라고요?
I killed almost 20 people.
나는 거의 20명을 죽였습니다.
I didn't leave any evidence,
증거도 남기지 않았는데
and I figured out an easy way to take care of the bodies,
그리고 시체를 관리하는 쉬운 방법을 알아냈어요.
so why take a risk?
그럼 왜 위험을 감수합니까?
So it wasn't because you were afraid?
그럼 두려워서 그런 게 아니었나요?
No.
아니요.
It was not out of fear.
그것은 두려움 때문이 아니었습니다.
It was because I could kill them unhindered at my place.
내가 있는 곳에서 방해받지 않고 그들을 죽일 수 있었기 때문이다.
Why did you stop receiving treatment for your epilepsy?
뇌전증 치료를 중단한 이유는 무엇입니까?
I was there too.
나도 거기에 있었다.
Darn it.
젠장.
So you saw everything.
그래서 당신은 모든 것을 보았습니다.
Even being hospitalized didn't help.
병원에 입원해도 소용이 없었습니다.
Nothing was going my way.
내 뜻대로 되는 게 하나도 없었어요.
The only thing I could do was kill.
내가 할 수 있는 유일한 일은 죽이는 것뿐이었다.
I guess you had many aspirations.
많은 포부를 가지셨을 것 같아요.
When I was young,
내가 어렸을 때,
I wanted to be an artist.
나는 예술가가되고 싶었습니다.
But you need money to do that.
하지만 그러려면 돈이 필요해요.
So I thought about becoming a cop...
그래서 경찰이 되려고 생각했는데..
A cop?
경찰?
Power, influence, and money.
권력, 영향력, 그리고 돈.
They are the most important things in life.
그것들은 인생에서 가장 중요한 것들입니다.
Without it, you get looked down on.
그것이 없으면 당신은 무시당하게 됩니다.
But...
하지만...
aren't cops just a corrupt group of people too?
경찰도 부패한 집단 아닌가요?
Why do you think that?
왜 그렇게 생각하세요?
When I forged the police ID card...
경찰 신분증을 위조했을 때..
and used it to get money, people gave it up so naturally.
돈을 벌기 위해 사용하다 보니 사람들은 너무나 자연스럽게 포기하게 되었습니다.
This world where the wealthy get rich illegally...
부자가 불법적으로 부자가 되는 이 세상...
women live promiscuously...
여자들은 방탕하게 살아요...
and civil servants live like bugs.
공무원은 벌레처럼 산다.
They all have to be punished!
그 사람들 다 처벌받아야 해!
If I don't do it...
내가 안 하면...
who will punish them?
누가 그들을 처벌할 것인가?
You talk as if you are implementing social justice.
마치 사회 정의를 구현하는 것처럼 이야기합니다.
Do you have the right to do that?
당신에게는 그렇게 할 권리가 있습니까?
Well, I wouldn't say I have the right...
글쎄, 나한테 그런 권리가 있다고는 말 못하겠는데...
but killing is sort of like a job of mine.
하지만 살인은 내 일과 비슷해요.
Your job?
당신의 직업?
I'm doing the job that needs to be done.
나는 해야 할 일을 하고 있습니다.
So...
그래서...
is that why you only chose those who were weaker than you?
그래서 너보다 약한 놈들만 뽑은 거야?
You know very well yourself...
당신 자신도 잘 알고 있군요...
just how pathetic that is, right Gu Young Chun?
얼마나 한심한지요, 구영춘씨?
What?
무엇?
You have no right to punish them.
당신은 그들을 처벌할 권리가 없습니다.
That goes for everyone else too.
그건 다른 사람들에게도 마찬가지입니다.
Even if they committed a crime, they should be punished...
범죄를 저질러도 처벌을 받아야 하는데...
within the limits of the law, not by you.
귀하가 아닌 법의 한계 내에서.
So don't try to justify your horrible actions...
그러니 당신의 끔찍한 행동을 정당화하려고 하지 마세요...
with that ridiculous reasoning.
그 말도 안되는 논리로.
- You're wrong! - Gu Young Chun.
- 당신은 틀렸어! - 구영춘.
You are...
당신은 ...
just a pathetic murderer.
그냥 불쌍한 살인자일 뿐이야.
Gu Young Chun is just a nasty scumbag...
구영춘은 그냥 더러운 쓰레기야...
who gave divine meaning to his actions...
그의 행동에 신성한 의미를 부여하신 분...
then substituted his helplessness with anger and attacked people.
그런 다음 그의 무력함을 분노로 대체하고 사람들을 공격했습니다.
(Show the right path and protect with warmth.)
(올바른 길을 보여주고 따뜻함으로 지켜주세요.)
- That was tough, right? - No, it was fine.
- 힘들었죠? - 아뇨, ​​괜찮았어요.
Would you like to get dinner?
저녁을 드시겠어요?
Yes, let's do that.
예, 그렇게 합시다.
What are you doing? Song Ha Young.
뭐하세요? 송하영.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
Yes, I'm okay.
네, 괜찮아요.
Pace yourself.
속도를 조절하세요.
He said killing was his job.
그는 살인이 그의 직업이라고 말했습니다.
Who did?
누가 그랬나요?
Gu Young Chun?
구영춘?
What a crazy scumbag.
정말 미친 쓰레기입니다.
Before this, I never heard from anyone...
그 전에는 누구한테도 소식을 들은 적이 없었어요...
what they studied in order to cut up the bodies...
시신을 자르기 위해 연구한 것들...
and what they felt while mutilating them.
그리고 그들이 그들을 절단하면서 느꼈던 것.
On top of that...
게다가...
Never in my life...
내 인생에 한번도...
did I see a face so full of the sense of superiority and joy.
나는 우월감과 기쁨으로 가득 찬 얼굴을 보았습니까?
You did good work.
당신은 좋은 일을 했습니다.
Captain.
선장.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Why was it me of all people?
왜 모든 사람 중에 나였습니까?
Why did it have to be me...
왜 나여야만 했을까...
for a job like this?
이런 직업을 위해서?
Ha Young, that...
하영아 그거...
You said you carried a lighter with you for emergencies, right?
비상용으로 라이터를 가지고 다닌다고 했죠?
Would I feel a little better...
기분이 좀 나아졌을까...
if I get drunk?
내가 취하면?
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I'll get going first.
나 먼저 갈게.
(Seoul Metropolitan Police Agency)
(서울지방경찰청)
- Hello, sir. - Yes, hello.
- 안녕하세요, 선생님. - 네, 안녕하세요.
Sit down.
앉으세요.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
What did the prosecution say about Gu Young Chun?
검찰은 구영천에 대해 뭐라고 밝혔나?
Gu Young Chun, that punk.
구영춘, 그 새끼야.
He's giving them a hard time too.
그 사람도 그들에게 힘든 시간을 주고 있어요.
A leopard can't change its spots.
표범은 자신의 반점을 바꿀 수 없습니다.
What's with everyone's looks?
다들 외모가 뭐야?
Oh, right. I know very well that quote speaks directly to me.
아, 그렇죠. 나는 그 인용문이 나에게 직접적으로 말하는 것을 잘 알고 있습니다.
- Gosh. - My goodness.
- 이런. - 맙소사.
Oh, another thing.
아, 또 다른 것.
When you write up Gu Young Chun's case report...
구영천 사건보고서를 쓰다 보면..
we were given an order...
우리는 명령을 받았습니다 ...
to also write the lessons we learned from this investigation.
또한 이번 조사를 통해 배운 교훈을 기록합니다.
Think hard about what we didn't do well at...
우리가 뭘 잘 못했는지 곰곰이 생각해보세요...
and what we did good...
그리고 우리가 잘한 일은...
and prepare for a meeting to discuss them.
그리고 그것들을 논의하기 위한 회의를 준비합니다.
- Got it? - Yes, sir.
- 알았어요? - 네, 선생님.
(Pureumae Park, Dongjak-gu)
(동작구 푸른매공원)
It was at night.
밤이었습니다.
(Chungmun-dong, Dobong-gu)
(도봉구 충문동)
Song Ha Young, that snake.
송하영, 그 뱀.
He's not still using the special promotion...
아직도 특별 프로모션을 사용하지 않고 있어요...
to make your life harder, right?
네 인생을 더 힘들게 만들려고 그러는 거 맞지?
What are you saying all of a sudden?
갑자기 무슨 말을 하는 거야?
You know how fast I can pick things up.
내가 얼마나 빨리 물건을 집어들 수 있는지 아시잖아요.
I'm just saying this because I've been watching the two of you...
그냥 너희 둘을 지켜보고 있어서 하는 말인데..
since I joined the team, and things seemed awkward.
팀에 들어오고 나서부터 뭔가 어색한 것 같더라고요.
Song Ha Young, that guy. He only pretends to be righteous.
송하영, 그 사람. 그는 단지 의로운 척만 할 뿐입니다.
I already know how good he is at betraying people.
나는 그가 사람을 얼마나 잘 배신하는지 이미 알고 있습니다.
Hey.
여기요.
Even after what your perp, Jung Soo Chang, said that day,
그날 범인 장정수씨가 한 말에도 불구하고
I never told anybody else.
나는 다른 사람에게 말한 적이 없습니다.
But you don't know what Song Ha Young will do.
그런데 송하영이 무슨 짓을 할지 모르잖아요.
Who...
누구...
told you what?
뭐라고 말했어?
Jung Soo Chang.
장정수.
Did you forget?
잊어버렸나요?
Come on, you can't forget that.
자, 그걸 잊지 마세요.
He was blabbing on and on about it during my interrogation.
그는 내가 심문하는 동안 계속해서 그것에 대해 비난했습니다.
I can tell you now that I beat him up so badly...
내가 그 사람을 너무 심하게 때렸다는 걸 이제 말할 수 있겠네요...
that he wouldn't speak up again. You didn't know, did you?
그 사람이 다시는 말을 하지 않겠다고 하더군요. 당신은 몰랐죠?
You got promoted thanks to me.
나 덕분에 승진했구나.
(External Affairs, Small Conference Room)
(대외협력실, 소회의실)
Let's find out if you'll also become a big shot.
당신도 대박이 될 수 있는지 알아봅시다.
Darn you.
젠장.
Come in.
들어오세요.
(Save Electricity)
(전기 절약)
Hey. Is something going on?
안녕. 무슨 일이 일어나고 있나요?
I was on my way home,
집에 가는 길이었는데,
but I saw the lights on,
그런데 불이 켜져 있는 걸 봤어요.
so I decided to stop by.
그래서 나는 들르기로 결정했습니다.
You're still here.
당신은 아직 여기 있어요.
I had to check something.
뭔가 확인해야 했어요.
For the Southwestern Case?
남서부 사건의 경우?
Oh, yes.
아, 그렇죠.
We first thought Gu Young Chun did that,
처음엔 구영춘이 그런 줄 알았는데,
but our team is also turning the case...
하지만 우리 팀도 사건을 뒤집고 있어요...
in a different direction now.
지금은 다른 방향으로.
I requested cooperation.
협조를 요청했습니다.
I'll let you know if we have any other reports.
다른 제보가 있으면 알려드리겠습니다.
I see. Thank you.
알겠어요. 감사합니다.
These horrible criminals...
이 무서운 범죄자들...
continue to swarm out.
계속해서 떼를 지어 나갑니다.
They are.
그렇습니다.
You should go home and get some rest.
집에 가서 좀 쉬어야 해요.
It'll take some time for you to heal.
치유되려면 시간이 좀 걸릴 거예요.
I have had...
나는 ...
a misunderstanding about you, Inspector Song.
송 경위님에 대한 오해입니다.
A misunderstanding?
오해?
Right before my promotion,
승진 직전,
I said I wanted to right the wrong...
잘못된 것을 바로잡고 싶다고 말했는데…
because I did not catch Jung Soo Chang.
장정수를 잡지 못했기 때문이다.
Do you remember what you said?
당신이 말한 것을 기억하십니까?
Why do you suddenly ask?
갑자기 왜 물어보나요?
I said you caught Jung Soo Chang.
장정수를 잡았다고 하더군요.
Yes.
예.
You said...
당신은 말했다 ...
the same thing back then.
그때도 마찬가지다.
I know you've had a tough time because of that stalker.
그 스토커 때문에 당신이 힘든 시간을 보냈다는 걸 알아요.
I also know how people around you just laughed it off...
주변 사람들이 어떻게 웃어넘겼는지 나도 알아요...
and said it's because you're popular.
그리고 당신이 인기가 있기 때문이라고 하더군요.
But it's also true that I was afraid...
하지만 두려웠던 것도 사실이에요...
even though I was a detective who should be arresting the perp.
범인을 잡아야 할 형사인데도 말이죠.
Also,
또한,
someone became a witness to that moment, which made me...
그 순간 누군가가 목격자가 되었고, 그게 나를...
embarrassed...
당황하다...
and tormented.
그리고 괴로워했다.
Well, detectives are humans too.
뭐, 형사도 사람이니까요.
Everyone faces such a moment of horror.
누구나 그런 공포의 순간을 마주하게 된다.
The same goes for me too.
나도 마찬가지다.
I only stopped you from getting hurt.
난 네가 상처받는 걸 막았을 뿐이야.
You were the one...
당신은 바로 그 사람이었습니다 ...
who arrested him, Captain Yoon.
그를 체포한 윤대위.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
I think...
내 생각엔...
I wanted to say that.
나는 그것을 말하고 싶었다.
Well, of course, you may not be curious...
물론, 궁금하지 않을 수도 있지만...
about what I think.
내가 생각하는 것에 대해.
I only did my job.
나는 내 일을 했을 뿐이에요.
All right, then.
그럼요.
Please excuse me.
실례합니다.
All right. Goodbye.
괜찮은. 안녕히 가세요.
(Seoul Metropolitan Police Agency)
(서울지방경찰청)
(Southwestern Serial Murder Case)
(남서부 연쇄 살인 사건)
(Special Crime Squad 1, Team 1)
(특수수사대 1팀)
(Hwanghwa-dong Case)
(황화동 사건)
(Facial Composite)
(얼굴 합성)
(Stay tuned for the epilogue.)
(에필로그를 기대해주세요.)
(Through the Darkness, Part 2)
(어둠을 뚫고 2부)
What will we be left with?
우리는 무엇을 남길 것인가?
Our hearts break into pieces...
우리의 마음은 산산조각이 난다...
while looking into the darkness, so how can we fill that void?
어둠을 들여다보며 그 공백을 어떻게 채울 수 있을까요?
I also thought long and hard about it.
나 또한 그것에 대해 오랫동안 열심히 생각했다.
But you know,
하지만 아시다시피,
no cigarettes or drinks can fill that void.
그 어떤 담배나 음료도 그 공백을 채울 수 없습니다.
That's why I want to say this.
그래서 나는 이렇게 말하고 싶다.
Can we continue to contemplate it...
계속해서 생각해 볼 수 있을지...
and look for the answer?
답을 찾으시겠습니까?
For now, let us focus on the suffering victims.
지금은 고통받는 피해자들에게 집중해 보겠습니다.
Okay, I will.
알았어, 그럴게.
I'm the one who picked you.
당신을 선택한 사람은 바로 나입니다.
You asked, "Why was it me of all people?"
당신은 “왜 나였나요?”라고 물었습니다.
My heart dropped as soon as you said that.
그 말을 하자마자 심장이 쿵 떨어졌어요.
I've been feeling heavy since.
그 이후로 몸이 무거워졌습니다.
I'm sorry. That's not what I meant.
죄송합니다. 내 말은 그런 뜻이 아니었어.
But you know, I was also glad.
하지만 나도 기뻤습니다.
It felt like you finally...
드디어 너인 것 같았어...
began to share what's in your heart with me.
당신의 마음속에 있는 것을 나와 공유하기 시작했습니다.
Was I that reserved?
내가 그렇게 예약되어 있었나요?
At this point in time,
이 시점에서,
you have me as a captain,
당신은 나를 선장으로 삼고 있습니다.
and we have the smart and kind Jung Chu Chu... Goodness.
그리고 우리에겐 똑똑하고 친절한 정추츄가 있는데... 맙소사.
We have Woo Ju too.
우주도 있어요.
And Superintendent Baek, who loves the Analysis Team...
그리고 분석팀을 사랑하는 백경감님..
as well as Gil Pyo.
길표도 그렇고.
Don't keep everything to yourself.
모든 것을 혼자만 간직하지 마세요.
If you get mad, scream out.
화가 나면 소리를 지르세요.
And start swearing too.
그리고 욕도 시작하세요.
Do whatever you want. I can deal with it.
원하는 대로 하세요. 내가 처리할 수 있어요.
I'll do that.
내가 그렇게 할게요.
I'll broaden my search and look for other cases...
검색 범위를 넓혀서 다른 사례도 찾아봐야겠습니다...
similar to the Southwestern Case.
남서부 사례와 유사합니다.
I do feel bad...
기분이 안좋아요...
for choosing you for this work.
이 일을 위해 당신을 선택해 주셔서 감사합니다.
But even if I went back in time, I'd still choose you.
하지만 시간을 되돌려도 나는 여전히 당신을 선택할 거예요.
Me too.
저도요.
You know how cheesy this is, right?
이게 얼마나 뻔한 일인지 아시죠?
Yes, I do. I know.
네, 그렇습니다. 알아요.
I'm just saying it over a drink.
그냥 술 한잔하면서 하는 말이에요.
Woo Ju, do you want one more drink too?
우주야, 너도 한잔 더 할래?
Goodness. Woo Ju.
선량. 우주.
We're looking for a psycho who's lurking around...
우리는 주변에 숨어있는 사이코를 찾고 있어요...
the Southwestern area with a knife in his hand.
손에 칼을 들고 남서부 지역.
The weapon continues to change.
무기는 계속 바뀌는데요.
It's good for you to focus on work, but we're in for a long haul.
일에 집중하는 것은 좋지만 우리는 오랜 시간 동안 일해야 합니다.
The more we delay this and hesitate,
이것을 미루고 망설일수록
the more the victims will increase.
그럴수록 피해자는 늘어날 것이다.
Special Crime Squad also wants to catch the culprit.
특수수사대도 범인을 잡고 싶어한다.
His MO evolved by studying his crimes.
그의 MO는 범죄를 연구함으로써 진화했습니다.
What's next?
다음은 무엇입니까?
- What are you doing? - Copying him.
- 뭐하세요? - 따라해요.
I'm trying to become the culprit.
나는 범인이 되려고 노력하고 있습니다.
For the first time,
처음으로,
I'm starting to wonder if what I did was right.
내가 한 일이 옳은 것인지 궁금해지기 시작했습니다.
(Next Friday at 10pm)
(다음주 금요일 밤 10시)